<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in Christ-Church before His Excellency the lord deputy and the honorable House of Peers, October the 8th, 1695 being the day appointed for a solemn thanksgiving for the taking the strong cittadel of Namur, and for the other happy successes of His Majesty's forces, and those of his allies in Flanders this campaign / by Edward, Lord Bishop of Down &amp; Connor.</title>
            <author>Walkington, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67307</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W458</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38411</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17356843</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17356843</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106444</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67307)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106444)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1106:36)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in Christ-Church before His Excellency the lord deputy and the honorable House of Peers, October the 8th, 1695 being the day appointed for a solemn thanksgiving for the taking the strong cittadel of Namur, and for the other happy successes of His Majesty's forces, and those of his allies in Flanders this campaign / by Edward, Lord Bishop of Down &amp; Connor.</title>
                  <author>Walkington, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 17 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Norman, Eliphal Dobson, and Patrick Campbell, booksellers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Thursday, the 10th of October, 1695. By the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in Parliament assembled. Ordered, that the Earl of Droghedah ... be desired to cause his sermon to be printed. Gerard Bor. cler. Parliamentor."--T.p. verso.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXXXV, 20 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, Irish --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106444:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106444:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED In CHRIST-CHURCH BEFORE His Excellency the Lord Deputy, AND THE Honorable Houſe of Peers; <hi>October</hi> the <hi>8th.</hi> 1695.</p>
            <p>Being the Day Appointed for a Solemn Thanksgiving for the Taking the Strong Cittadel of <hi>NAMUR,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the other happy Succeſſes of His Majeſty's Forces, and thoſe of His Allies in <hi>Flanders</hi> this Campaign,</p>
            <p>By <hi>EDWARD,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Down</hi> &amp; <hi>Connor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>DUBLIN,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Norman, Eliphal Dobſon,</hi> and <hi>Patrick Campbell,</hi> Bookſellers. 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:106444:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Thurſday, <date>the <hi>10th</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> 1695.</date> By the Lords Spiritual and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral in Parliament Aſſembled.</dateline> Ordered,</opener>
            <p>That the Earl of <hi>Droghedah,</hi> and the Lord Viſcount <hi>Bleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nton,</hi> do give the Thanks of this Houſe to the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Down</hi> for his Sermon Preached before this Houſe at <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> on <hi>Tueſday</hi> laſt, being the Day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for a General Thankſgiving for his Majeſty's, and his Allies, ſo great Succeſs in Taking the Town and Caſtle of <hi>Namur,</hi> and preſerving His Majeſty's ſacred Perſon from the many dangers to which he was ſo frequently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd during the Siege; and that his Lordſhip be deſired to cauſe his Sermon to be Printed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Gerard Bor. Cler. Parliamentor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106444:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> PREACHED In Chriſt-Church, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſal. 135. later part of the <hi>20th</hi> Verſe.</bibl>
               <q>Ye that fear the Lord, Bleſs the Lord.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Pſalm out of which I have choſen theſe words, is a Hymn of Praiſe; and it is obſervable in the manner, or ſtile of theſe Hymns, that the Compoſer generally calls upon all around him, upon irrational, and inanimate things, ſometimes, as well as upon perſons, to joyn with him, in the Encomium of the great perſon whom he celebrates; and the holy Pſalmiſt, who very well underſtood all the Schemes and Elegancies of Poeſie, ſometimes does the like, as when he calls up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>every thing that has breath,</hi> upon the <hi>Sun, Moon,</hi> and <hi>Stars,</hi> the <hi>Mountains</hi> and <hi>Rivers,</hi> to <hi>praiſe the Lord.</hi> But in this Pſalm he calls upon thoſe who are under a more ſtrict and peculiar obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as well as acted by a more Zealous, and ready Diſpoſition, to <hi>praiſe him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> The <hi>Servants</hi> of the Lord, ſuch as <hi>ſtand in the houſe of the Lord,</hi> in the <hi>Courts of the houſe of his God.</hi> Then he goes on to deſcribe the great and mighty things, that God had done for his People, the <hi>Tokens</hi> and <hi>Wonders,</hi> the <hi>Mercies</hi> and Deliverances, the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106444:3"/> Victories and Succeſſes over their numerous, and powerful Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: From thence he proceeds to deſpiſe, and deride the ſilly I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols of the Heathens, and to ſhew that it is the greateſt folly and ſtupidity in the World, to expect any thing like theſe from them; That thoſe that <hi>make 'em,</hi> are <hi>like unto 'em,</hi> and ſo are all <hi>they that put their truſt in 'em.</hi> And at laſt he calls upon thoſe who were the remarkable Objects, as well as the living Monuments of God's goodneſs and mercy, to joyn with him. That the whole <hi>Houſe of Iſrael,</hi> eſpecially the <hi>Houſe of Levi,</hi> would bleſs the Lord: That all that <hi>fear him,</hi> that is every one, that has a true Senſe of Piety, would ſhow it, in the Exerciſe of this great Duty of publick wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, invocation, and praiſe of his moſt holy Name, for his goodneſs and mercy. <hi>Ye that fear the Lord, Bleſs the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where we are not to underſtand by fear, that awful, uneaſy paſſion of dread, and terrour, which is apt to ariſe from a concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the divine Juſtice and Vengeance, but we are to take it in a larger Senſe, for a certain habit, or diſpoſition of mind, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines men to a Religious Reverence of the divine Eſſence and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes. The holy Scripture underſtand's ſometimes, by the fear of the Lord, the whole of Religion, <hi>Gen. 20. 11. Surely the fear of God, is not in this place.</hi> Theſe are the words of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who was afraid that the men of <hi>Gerar</hi> would ſlay him upon the account of his Wife, becauſe they had no ſenſe of Religion amongſt 'em; The wiſe man tells us, that the <hi>fear of the Lord is the beginning of Knowledge:</hi> and the Pſalmiſt calls men to him, that he may teach them the <hi>Fear of the Lord,</hi> that is, that he may inſtruct 'em in the duties of Religion, nay ſometimes the holy Writers expeſs by the fear of the Lord, ſome acts of the mind, that are excluſive of that paſſion: <hi>Prov. 14. 26. In the fear of the Lord, is ſtrong Confidence,</hi> and <hi>Act.</hi> 9. 31. We are told of walking in the <hi>Fear of the Lord, and Comfort.</hi> Now <hi>Comfort,</hi> and <hi>Confidence,</hi> having nothing to do with <hi>Fear,</hi> according to the uſual ſtrict Senſe of the word: by the fear of the Lord in theſe places muſt needs be meant a habit of Piety, or that Religious Reſpect, and Reverence that is due to God.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:106444:3"/>
            <p>And as we are not to take fear in this place, in the ſtrict Senſe of the word; So neither are we to underſtand by bleſſing the Lord, the bare act of praiſing his holy Name with our lips only, which is a thing may poſſibly be done when our hearts are far from him, but a firm ſettl'd habit of thankfulneſs for all his Favours, which upon fit and proper occaſions, ſhall break out into ſuch acts as denote our honour, and eſteem of him before men, and our Zeal for his Glory; ſuch as publick declarations of our gratitude, for his general favours towards us, and our ſolemn praiſes and thankſgivings, for his more immediate and extroardinary Mercies, and Deliverances.</p>
            <p>The Words being thus underſtood, offer to our conſideration theſe two things, <hi>1ſt</hi> here is a duty injoyn'd, to <hi>Bleſs the Lord. 2dly.</hi> Here is a certain habit or diſpoſition of mind, which they are ſuppos'd to have, that are call'd upon to this duty, and that is <hi>The Fear of the Lord.</hi> Now becauſe this laſt is but ſuppos'd here only, and the former is look'd upon as a conſequent of it, I ſhall begin with the later; That habit of Religious Worſhip and Reverence towards God, which is the foundation of the devotional part of Religion, concerning which, I ſhall inquire 1ſt, what are the ſeeds from whence it grows, or what are the conſiderations from whence ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and thinking men reaſon themſelves into this habit of Piety and Devotion towards God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> I ſhall conſider the duty it ſelf, of Bleſſing God, and in what it conſiſts; and when this is done, I ſhall in the <hi>3d</hi> place endeavour to ſhew you that they who thus fear the Lord, are the fitteſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the World to bleſs and praiſe him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> Then, I look upon this habit of fearing God to be a dictate of the Law of Nature, as much as any part of the moral Law whatſoever, if we ſuppoſe the being of a God, which muſt be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, as the Foundation of all certain Truths, as well as of all Religion.</p>
            <p>Now, as to the being of a God, the conſtant Senſe, and practice of every Age, and Nation of the World, that we can have any manner of account of in ſtory, do abundantly confirm this, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as if here and there, an Atheiſt, or Anti-religioniſt be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106444:4"/> he ſeems to ſtand upon Record, as ſome monſtrous, and uncouth production, for which humane Nature, is not accountable, but it may be ſaid perhaps that this ſenſe of a Deity, and the pious regards, that have been conſtantly paid to it, is a notion invented, and inſtill'd, into the minds of men, by cunning Politicians, who found it difficult to Govern the World without it; I confeſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that to Govern the World without it, is not only difficult, but impoſſible, which is no diſparagment, but a great honour to Religion, and a great Argument of the truth of it, but it does not therefore follow that it was contriv'd by Politicians; for beſides that, it is very hard to conceive, that all the Politicians of every Age and Nation in the world ſhould ſo luckily hit upon the ſame State Maxim, who differ almoſt in every thing in the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides. I think it is ſufficiently unaccountable, how the moſt rude and barbarous Nations, and ſuch amongſt 'em, as never convers'd with a Polititian in their lives, ſhou'd, upon the firſt dawning of Reaſon, diſcover this Notion in their minds, and expreſs it in their practice.</p>
            <p>It remains therefore, that Piety and Devotion towards God, and the neceſſity of our Addreſſes to him, which is the thing here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt by the Fear of the Lord, is a dictate of the Law of Nature, and is indeed a Conſequence eaſily deducible from our ſenſe of our own wants, and of the divine goodneſs, and Power to redreſs 'em. And that theſe wants are great, and this goodneſs, and Power (to which we apply our ſelves for relief) infinite, are two of the firſt, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal truths to which the humane underſtanding does clearly and diſtinctly attain.</p>
            <p>But we Chriſtians, whoſe underſtandings are aſſiſted by an additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal, and greater light, the Revelation of the will of God, made to us in his holy Word, are not only diſtinctly inform'd of this matter in general, but the nature of our wants, the ſeveral kinds, degrees, and occaſions of 'em, the miſery of our Condition, if they be not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs't, the infinite power, and unſpeakable mercies of God, the great and ſignal inſtances of his favour to ſinful men, his kind, and gracious invitations of thoſe who have provok'd him, and his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106444:4"/> of receiving 'em, as oft as they make their applications in the way that he has preſcrib'd, are all reval'd to us in Scripture, and every one of theſe, is a clear, and forcible Argument upon us, to fix in our minds this <hi>Fear of the Lord,</hi> this habit of Reverence, and this reſolution of waiting upon him in his holy Ordinances, for a ſupply and continuance of his benefits.</p>
            <p>If we look into our wants, they are ſuch, as either relate to our <hi>Spiritual,</hi> or <hi>Temporal</hi> Conditions.</p>
            <p>Our Spiritual Condition is very deplorable by the fall of our firſt Parents, and by that <hi>fomes peccati,</hi> as the School-men call it, which they have communicated to our Natures. It has like a ſtrong diſeaſe, corrupted our whole maſs, and ſpead it's ill influence thro' all the faculties of our ſouls. It has blinded our underſtandings with error and prejudice, and perverted our wills, with our luſts &amp; paſſions, inſomuch that ſcarce our moſt holy duties, are free from ſome or other ill conſequence of this unhappy State. This is the cauſe, why, <hi>when we are about to do good, evil is preſent with us,</hi> this is the <hi>War in our members,</hi> this is the <hi>Carnal luſt that reſiſts the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> and is <hi>at Enmity with God.</hi> A ſett of Expreſſions, that do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly well repreſent the great power that this pollution of our Natures has upon us, and ſeem to intimate, that our ſlavery under it, is ſo great, that it comes near to deſtroy, even the freedom of our wills: In ſhort, this is it which in our Prayers, deads our Faith, our fervency, our truſt, and affiance in God, and our cloſe attention upon that holy duty. This is it that caſts in impertinent thoughts, looſe deſires, wrong ends, and the like, which are as ſo many ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes in our Sacrifice. This is it that in our hearing, or reading the divine truths, poſſeſſes our minds with prejudice, inadverten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, miſapplication, and ſometimes with down-right Infidelity, which makes it a <hi>Savour not of Life unto Life, but of Death unto Death,</hi> to minds ſo fatally corrupted. In fine, this is it that in our moſt ſerious meditations upon our great eternal concern, make us light, and unſettl'd, driving to no point, or iſſue, fixing no firm, immoveable Reſolution of a ſincere uniforn obedience to the will of God.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:106444:5"/>
            <p>Againſt this deplorable condition, we have no relief, but by our applications and addreſſes to the Throne of Grace, zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and frequent acts of which, make up this habit of Piety, or <hi>fear of the Lord,</hi> which makes us acquainted with his great and glorious Attributes, as that his infinite power makes him able, and his infinite goodneſs willing to relieve us, which he does by ſending the <hi>Comforter,</hi> the bleſſed Spirit of Grace, by whoſe aſſiſtance and influence, we have full redreſs of all our wants, and hardſhips. This powerful influence of the Spirit of God, like a good medicine, diffuſes its vertue every where, applys it ſelf to every diſaffected part: It bears down before it the dulneſs, and prejudice of our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, with the ſtrength and clearneſs of the divine truths, and with a ſweet and endearing violence, it ſets upon our wills<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and unruly affections, and ſubdues 'em to the obedience of Faith. This efficacy of the Spirit of God upon the minds of men, is call'd by the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> the <hi>writing the Law in the heart,</hi> and <hi>putting it into the inward parts:</hi> It is call'd by our Saviour, <hi>the Father's teaching,</hi> the holy Spirit's <hi>convincing</hi> men, <hi>of ſin, of righteouſneſs, and judgment:</hi> and the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it, <hi>the ſpiritual revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Wiſdom, out of the Word, unto the Conſcience.</hi> And thus I have ſhew'd you the reaſonableneſs and neceſſity of Piety, or the devotional part of Religion, which is here call'd the <hi>Fear of the Lord,</hi> with regard to our ſpiritual wants, and the way of redreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing 'em.</p>
            <p>Our temporal wants will be conſidered, either as we are ſingle perſons, or as we are united into a Body-Politick, under the ſame common Laws and Government.</p>
            <p>As to our temporal wants, which concern us, as we are ſingle perſons, they are ſuch as make us to depend upon providence, for the ſmalleſt things we enjoy. The very preſervation of our Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, is but a continued creation, which makes infinite providence as neceſſary to preſerve, as infinite power to create us. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon accidents of humane life, are ſo obvious, and yet ſo unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that no man living can either by his wiſdom foreſee, or by his power and greatneſs prevent 'em. The health and vigour of the ſtrong, the plenty of the rich, and the honours of the great and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106444:5"/> powerful, are ſuch, as the poſſeſſors of 'em cannot command their ſtay; nay, whilſt they do enjoy 'em, they generally have thoſe cares, and anxieties to attend 'em, that uſually embitter the ſweeteſt of 'em. We have read indeed of a certain perfect happineſs, which a wiſe man was to create within himſelf, even in this world, without any regard to any thing without him, or above him: to arrive at which, did ſufficiently exerciſe the wits, and expoſe the follies of ſome of the ancient Philoſophers, amongſt whom, ſome were to feel no pain in a fitt of the Gout or Stone; nor to know any difference between <hi>Phalaris's Bull,</hi> and a cool <hi>Grotto:</hi> All which was but a meer notion, that never came to any more than a few empty words: For ſome of the great pretenders to it have ſhew'd themſelves but men, and weak ones too, in ſome of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary hardſhips and calamities of humane life: Contentment with our condition, (tho a thing much talk'd of by many, and tho many ſpecious Rules are laid down for the attainment of it) being ſcarce ever known on this ſide Heaven, inſomuch that nothing can poſſibly make any condition of life eaſy, or ſupportable to any man, that has not an eye to ſomething that can eaſe him of the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that attend the acquiſition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and of the griefs and anxieties that follow the loſs of theſe worldly enjoyments; and that muſt be no other, than that great and glorious Being who commands 'em all, and diſpoſeth of 'em as ſeems beſt to his <hi>Godly Wiſdom.</hi> And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever fixeth this Principle in his mind, and acts in purſuance of it, that creat's caſe, and ſatisfaction to himſelf, from the knowledge &amp; contemplation of this Wiſe and Almighty Being, and from an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire truſt, and dependance upon him, who has commanded him to make his addreſſes to him, and has promis'd to anſwer 'em; that's the wiſe man; that's he, that obſerves and conſiders well, what God commands by the mouth of the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah: Let not the wiſe man glory in his Wiſdom, neither let the mighty man glory in his might; let not the rich man glory in his Riches, but let him that glory's, glory in this, That he underſtandeth, and knoweth me, that I am the Lord, which exerciſe Loving-kindneſs, Judgment, and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs in the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:106444:6"/>
            <p>Neither do we ſtand leſs in need of the goodneſs, mercy, &amp; boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of God, as we are united into Societies, and bodies politick, under the ſame common Laws, and Government, than as we are ſingle perſons. Peace, plenty, trade, and commerce, fidelity, juſtice, amity, union of intereſts and affections amongſt our ſelves, a hearty zealous concern for the publick-weal, ſucceſs of our negotiations with our Allies and Friends, and victory over our Enemies, being all the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of Heaven; and as needful for the ſupport of a Kingdom, or Common-wealth, as food, raiment, health of body, and tranquility of mind for the behoof of any ſingle perſon. To whom then are we to apply our ſelves for all or any of theſe, but to that great and glorious Being, who has perfect knowledge, and wiſdom to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand our wants, unſpeakeable love, and goodneſs to incline him, and Almighty power to enable him to relieve us. Perfect Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, for his <hi>underſtanding is infinite,</hi> unſpeakable love, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; for he has told us that his <hi>mercy is over all his works,</hi> that he is the <hi>helper of the friendleſs,</hi> and tho' our Father and Mother <hi>forſake us,</hi> yet will not he; and Almighty Power, becauſe we are aſſur'd that all <hi>power belongs to God,</hi> that the Lord <hi>Jehovah is everlaſting ſtrength,</hi> and whatſoever he pleaſes he do's, <hi>both in Heaven, and Earth, and in the Sea, and in all deep places.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And theſe are the reaſons, directions, and incouragements to this great duty, of <hi>fearing the Lord,</hi> or that habit of Devotion, or Piety to God, which is here ſuppos'd in thoſe who are call'd upon to <hi>bleſs the Lord.</hi> We have diſcover'd it to be a dictate of the Law of Nature, and that it is founded upon the ſenſe of our own wants, both ſpiritual and temporal, and the wiſdom, power and goodneſs of God to redreſs 'em.</p>
            <p>I come now to conſider the Duty it ſelf, of <hi>Bleſſing God.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which, I ſhall ſhew you firſt, wherein it conſiſts. And then I ſhall ſhew you, that they that <hi>fear the Lord,</hi> are the only perſons rightly qualify'd for the performance of this duty.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Bleſsing the Lord</hi> then, We underſtand in this place, our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him all poſſible Honour in our thoughts, words and actions,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106444:6"/> and zealouſly endeavouring, every one in his ſtation, that others may do him honour.</p>
            <p>The ingredients of honour, are Love and Fear, and its object is goodneſs and Power united. Goodneſs without Power beget's Love only; and Power without Goodneſs beget's nothing but a ſlaviſh Fear, but both together, beget a certain affectionate Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and Eſteem, which we call honour. If this regard be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd to the thoughts only, it is no other, than a high eſtimation of thoſe Excellencies and Perfections, with which he is ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently endow'd, as to deſerve our Love and Reverence. If it break out into words, it becomes either praiſe, or thanks, and theſe denote our deſign to let others know the eſteem we have for the perſon whom we honour, together with the grateful ſenſe we have of his paſt Favours, and our readineſs to make the beſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns we can for any other, that he ſhall from time to time vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to confer upon us; but when it proceeds from Words to Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then it ſhews that we are in earneſt, then we ſhew the truth and ſincerity both of our hearts and words, and that we are reſolv'd to omit no occaſion, of demonſtrating to the World, the value we have for him whom we honour: And this is what is expected even by mortal men, to whom we pay this regard, and conſequently cannot be deny'd to God, in a more eminent manner, that is, in due proportion to his infinite power, and goodneſs. And tho that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that is confin'd to the thoughts (being no more than a due eſtimation of thoſe Excellencies, and Perfections that are in God, eſpecially his goodneſs and power) does at firſt appear to be an act of the Judgment only, and proceeding from a faculty that is not free, do's not ſeem to deſerve the name of a duty, can claim no praiſe, nor expect a reward, yet ſuch is the connexion of the will, and the underſtanding, and ſuch is their dependance, one upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in their operations, that they frequently partake of the vertues, and defects of each other, and not only the underſtanding guides the will, but the will inclines and diſpoſes the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, to good, as well as to evil acts, or elſe why ſhould infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity be a Sin, and Faith a Vertue, but that they are ſo, is certain: For the Scripture plainly declares 'em to be ſuch; and the reaſon
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106444:7"/> is plain, for as a docile and tractable diſpoſition of mind; humility, the Love of Truth, and a hearty endeavour to attain it, do beget Faith; So Pride and ill Nature, a Stupid Sloath, Obſtinacy, Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, and a reſolution to indulge out luſts and paſſions, are the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of Infidelity. We are not therefore to look upon that eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Judgment, by which we honour God in our thoughts, to be without value, for it is an excellent indication, of a mind rightly diſpos'd to the Love, and Fear of God, and the foundation or beginning of all the true Piety in the World. Theſe honorable thoughts of the divine power, and goodneſs, have a vaſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded Subject to employ 'em. We can caſt our eye upon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, whether in Heaven or Earth, or in the great deep, we can contemplate none of the great and amazing works of Art, or Nature, but they give us occaſion to admire and adore him, and what Hypotheſis, or Syſtem of the World have we ſeen that could give any tolerable account of the ſmalleſt appearance in Nature, without a God at the bottom of it? neither is his power and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs leſs viſible, in the moral, than in the natural World. The great and extraordinary<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> occurrences, which have ſometimes hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, contrary to the hopes and expectations of the moſt diſcerning men, ſuch as as have defeated the power, and baffl'd the Councels, of the Wiſe and Mighty, and have had ſuch demonſtrations of an over<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ruling providence, as ſufficiently ſhew'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the hand from whence they came. Theſe cannot but imploy the thoughts, of thoſe who honour God, and who muſt from hence reaſon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into this concluſion, that the Lord is great and powerful, that his Works are Wonderful, and that <hi>there is no end of his Greatneſs.</hi> Small and common matter, may paſs unregarded, but when the <hi>Arm of the Lord is made bare,</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Iſaia</hi> expreſſeth it, when it <hi>is lift up,</hi> and <hi>ſtretched out,</hi> who can but ſee it, and know it to be his? when theſe extraordinary works, of providence, are ſuch only, as denote his power, and greatneſs, then indeed the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ought to <hi>hear, and fear, and do no more preſumptiouſly:</hi> But when they are inſtances of his love and kindneſs too, this add's to our fear and reverence ſuch a proportion of Love and gratitude, as beget's the higheſt honour, and eſteem of him, and warms
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106444:7"/> our affections towards him, to that degree, that we count all things droſs in compariſon of him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>The hloy Scripture gives us ſuch an Idea of his power, and greatneſs, and of his mercy, and goodneſs, that it is an argument<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the moſt ſtrange ſtupidity in the world, not to be affected with it. Who can but fear and reverence <hi>the King of Kings,</hi> and <hi>Lord of Lords,</hi> who is <hi>glorious in holineſs, fearful in praiſes, doing won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: Who ruleth over all the Kingdoms of the Earth,</hi> and <hi>in whoſe hand is ſuch power, and might, that none is able to withſtand him; the Lord God, to whom belongs Greatneſs, and Power, and Glory, and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, and Majeſty, the Great, and Mighty, and Terrible God, who brings Princes to nothing, and makes the Judges of the Earth as Vanity; who takes the Wiſe in their own craftineſs, ſo that the counſel of the froward is carried headlong; who ſcatters his Enemies with a ſtrong Arm; who can make the worm</hi> Jacob <hi>to thraſh the Mountains, and beat 'em ſmall, and make the Hills as chaff; who commands the Sun, and it riſeth not, and ſeals up the Stars: Who is the only true and living God, and everlaſting King; at whoſe wrath, the Earth do's tremble; the Nations are not able to abide his Indignation.</hi> Who, I ſay, can be ſo ſtupid, as not to have his mind conſtantly affected with the thoughts of ſuch power and greatneſs; and who can be of ſo baſe and degenerate a frame of ſpirit, as not to be thoroughly affected likewiſe with a ſenſe of his infinite goodneſs and mercy; to whom we owe our being, preſervation, and all the benefits we enjoy, all the neceſſaries, conveniences, and pleaſures of this life, we have received from his bountiful hand: neither has he ſtopt here, but given us the reaſonable tenders, and well grounded hopes of a better life; who is not only merciful, and gracious, but libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and munificent: He not only pardons our ſins, that makes us unworthy of his mercies, but upon our repentance, and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he powers out <hi>his favours with a plentiful hand, gives freely, and upbraids no man, but keeps Covenant, and Mercy, and will never forſake them that ſeek him; who fills our hearts with food and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; who is the hope of Iſrael, and his Saviour, in the time of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; who has redeem'd us from the power of the Sword; and who will deliver us in ſix troubles, yea in ſeven, that no evill ſhall touch us.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:106444:8"/>
            <p>When theſe exalted and affectionate thoughts concerning God do break out into words (as they undoubtedly will do, if the heart be truly affected with the divine Favors) they become that which we call Praiſe and Thanksgiving; Praiſe for his Power, and Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and Thanksgiving for his Mercy, and Goodneſs; and theſe are the moſt noble and perfect parts of Divine Worſhip; for they are the imployment of the bleſſed in Heaven, in which they ſpend Eternity. So that they who deſire to go thither, methinks ſhould take a great deal of care and delight to habituate themſelves to that way of ſpending their time, which is to laſt with them for ever; for want of which, I am perſwaded it is, that we generally ſee thoſe who do not accuſtom themſelves to this duty, nor take any pleaſure in the performance of it, are ſo immers'd in this world, ſo burthen'd either with the pleaſures, or the toyls of it, that as they ſeem to think of none but this world, ſo neither is it probable that they deſire there ſhould be any other: But they that <hi>fear the Lord</hi> (who have thoroughly conſider'd his power and goodneſs, and that his promiſe of happineſs cannot be made good to 'em in this life, where the greateſt Riches, and Honours, have their troubles, and where the moſt refin'd pleaſures do cloy and ſurfeit, thoſe that moſt eagerly purſue 'em) have their minds imploy'd in the ſearch of more uoble, and exalted divertiſements, and therefore they endeavour to have a taſt of heaven, before they come there, which cannot be better done, than by imitation (as far as is poſſible) of thoſe that wait upon the Throne of God, <hi>ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hallelujahs to him that ſit's upon the Throne, and to the Lamb, for ever and ever:</hi> hence it is that in all well conſtituted Churches, Pſalms, and Hymns of praiſe and thankſgiving, are a great and principal part of the publick worſhip, the decent and Solemn per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of which, gives the minds of the Congregation, ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted notions of God, and has ſuch an Air of Zealous piety in the manner of expreſſing 'em that they generally make the deepeſt impreſſions upon the imagination, and memory of any part of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſervice.</p>
            <p>This ſhews the neceſſity &amp; reaſonableneſs of publick praiſe, and the great and aſtoniſhing mercies that we have had at the hand
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106444:8"/> of God, both Spirirtual, and Temporal, both private and publick, do ingage us to thankſgiving, which to an ingenuous mind is the moſt pleaſant of all duties. <hi>To hide the rigteouſneſs of God in his heart, and to conceal his loving kindneſs, and truth from the great Congregation,</hi> is what the Royal Pſalmiſt would not do; no, he would <hi>publiſh it with the voice of thankſgiving, and tell of all his wondrous works,</hi> he was reſolv'd <hi>to ſing of the mercies of the Lord for ever, and with his mouth would he make known his faithfulneſs to all generations, he would praiſe the name of God with a Song, and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify him with thankſgiving.</hi> To which duty no Nation upon the Earth has had more reaſonable, and frequent calls, than we. If Peace, Plenty, Liberty, and the moſt excellent conſtitution of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in the world, both Civil, and Eccleſiaſtical, are Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, what Nation under Heaven has ſuch reaſon as we have to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore and praiſe the divine goodneſs?</p>
            <p>If when our crying ſins, had juſtly provok'd God to turn his face away from us, he was pleas'd to turn again and revive us with the <hi>light of his Countenance.</hi> When <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> (with a Jeſuit in the prime Miniſtry to adviſe and direct it) was juſt ready to lay its Iron hands upon our Perſons and Properties, and <hi>Popery</hi> with all its nonſenſe and contradictions, ſeem'd prepar'd and authoriz'd, to debauch, or force our Conſciences: Then, for God to give us a King in his mercy, to protect us againſt theſe worſt of evils: A King, whoſe hereditary <hi>Right</hi> to our Monarchy made him dear to the Loyal; and his Wiſdom and Courage, formidable to the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent, and Diſaffected. A King, who ſeem'd fram'd by Heaven on purpoſe for this great Emergeney; for we may be ſure, that the <hi>right hand</hi> which <hi>hath the preeminence;</hi> that <hi>right hand of the Lord, that brings mighty things to paſs,</hi> will chuſe the fitteſt Inſtruments. A King who has anſwer'd this great deſign and call of Providence, by the moſt wiſe and effectual methods that we could wiſh or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agine, and reſtor'd us to Peace and Order, and the comforts of our wiſe and happy Government both Civil and Eccleſiaſtical, theſe are ſuch marks of the Divine Favour, that we have reaſon to believe our ſelves the peculiar care of Heaven. If to preſerve <hi>the Breath of our Noſtrils, the Anointed of the Lord</hi> from
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106444:9"/> the ſecret practices, and attempts, as well as from the open aſſaults of his, and our Enemies: <hi>If to cover his Head in the day of battle: If to teach his hands to war, and his fingers to fight,</hi> ſo, as to give him victory over the fierceſt of 'em, if to give him the conduct, and courage to attack &amp; defeat the boldeſt of their Troop, (as he has lately done) within their Walls and Retrenchments, be a mark of the divine favour; ſurely it is not only a reaſonable, and neceſſary, but it is a <hi>pleaſant thing to give thanks.</hi> He that can pretend to contain the ſenſe of ſuch mercies in his mind, without any publick demonſtrations of 'em, mucſt needs have but very ſlight touches of the Fear of the Lord, and but very weak and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>active notions of the <hi>Operations of his hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hope none that hear me this day are ſo regardleſs of theſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies as not to conſider from whoſe hands they come, how jealous he is of his honour, and how highly he will reſent ſo black an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, as that of refuſing to own 'em in publick; for a true and pious ſenſe of theſe, can never be buried in the mind, but muſt ſhew it ſelf in the congregation, in the voice of praiſe and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving to our great and glorious Benefactor.</p>
            <p>But as we are to bleſs the Lord in our thoughts and words, we muſt do it likewiſe in our actions, which is but to tell you in other word, that there is a moral as well as a devotional part of Religion, by which we do not only glorify God our ſelves, but we take care, that others <hi>ſeeing our good works, may glorify our Father which is in Heaven,</hi> for if we conſider God, as the Almighty Monarch, and wiſe Governor of the World, a ſincere uniform practice of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to his will, and obedience to his known Laws, is the moſt natural expreſſion of our honour to him, and the moſt accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table; For,</p>
            <p>Let us ſuppoſe a Courtier train'd up in all the moſt exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Arts of Court Ceremony, and demeanour; ſo obſervant of every look, and motion of his Prince, as to do him all the ſervices of attendance, and addreſs that may be, never failing to attend his riſing, and lying down, and ſo obſequious as never to miſs any
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106444:9"/> publick appearance that may do him Honour; and yet, at the ſame time, do's many extravagant, and illegal things, by oppreſſion of his fellow-ſubjects, by extortion, bribery, or cruelty, to the diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement and obloquie of the King and his Government. Such a perſon will never be ſo much lov'd, and valu'd by a wiſe Prince, as he that lives peaceably, juſtly and honeſtly in his ſtation, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the Laws of his Countrey, and promotes the obſervance of 'em by others, tho he do not always attend the King's preſence, nor pay his Court ſo conſtantly, and obſequiouſly as the other. Our Saviour tells us of thoſe, that have made <hi>long Prayers, but have devour'd Widows Houſes,</hi> and we have heard of ſome, who when they went to ſeek the Lord, in a manner more ſolemn than ordinary, had always ſome great miſchief to do: Such are ſo far from bleſſing, and glorifying God, that they bring a diſgrace upon his Worſhip; they are ſo far from being friends to his Intereſt, that they make his Enemies to blaſpheme him. <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, that he that <hi>oppreſſes the poor, reproaches God; but that he honour's God, who has mercy upon the poor.</hi> The wiſe Son of <hi>Syrach</hi> tells us, that <hi>he that keeps the Law, brings Offering enough; and he that takes heed to the Commandment, brings a Peace-Offering; he that requites a good turn, offers fine Flower; and he that gives Alms, ſacrificeth Praiſe;</hi> and that <hi>to forſake unrighteouſneſs, is a propitiation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as this way of mens glorifying God by their Actions, is the ſure way of making others to glorify him, ſo it is never more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markably effectual, than when men in eminent Station and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, are exemplary for their Vertue and Piety. Their light is ſet upon a high Candleſtick, and ſhines a great way, whilſt that which is not ſet up, but lies low, is either not ſeen, or not regarded. When our Law-givers and Magiſtrates ſhall hear, and obey that call of the Royal Prophet; <hi>Give unto the Lord O ye mighty I Give unto the Lord Glory, and Strength,</hi> Give unto the <hi>Lord the honour due unto his Name;</hi> then will inferiour Perſons quickly ſee, that there is a God, to whom they owe the ſame homage, which their ſuperiours ſo readily pay him; but when not only the good <hi>Lives</hi> but the good <hi>Laws,</hi> of our Magiſtrates, do manifeſtly tend to the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106444:10"/> Glory of God, and the promotion of Piety, then have we reaſon to believe, that God is in the midſt of us, that he preſides in our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, and will influence all our actions, for the pulick good. I do not pretend to preſcribe here, neither am I able to inſtruct the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wiſdom of this Nation, in any of the Political part of their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: all that I ſhall take upon me to ſay, is this, that there are two things very dear to God, his <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and his <hi>Worſhip;</hi> and I doubt not, but thoſe whoſe buſineſs it is to ſettle affairs upon the beſt and and ſureſt foundations, will take care of theſe in a peculiar manner.</p>
            <p>And thus I have ſhew'd you what it is to <hi>bleſs the Lord,</hi> it is to do him all poſſible honour our ſelves, in our thoughts, words and actions, and to endeavour, every one in his ſtation that others may do him honour.</p>
            <p>I come now to ſhew that they that <hi>Fcar the Lord,</hi> are the only perſons fit to perform this duty; <hi>For a fool</hi> (that is in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Language a wicked man) <hi>does not underſtand this, an unwiſe man does not conſider it,</hi> he has ſaid <hi>in his heart, there is no God,</hi> and therefore is certainly very unfit to honour him; he that would rob him of his Being, will pay but little deference to his At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes: Nay, tho he were convinc'd of the being of a God, yet in doing him honour, he is ſo out of his element, all the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal acts of Piety lye ſo odd and untoward to his genius, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, that we can expect from him but very low and worth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs performances in this kind: for this thing being ſuch as muſt not only deeply affect the thoughts, but ſhew it ſelf in mens words and actions, no man muſt think to do it, in a ſlight or perfuncto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry manner; for it is one of the grand and principal buſineſſes of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Life, and muſt be perform'd with all imaginable Zeal, and application. A hypocrite may for ſome by-ends, or to gain the reputation of Piety, attend the time, and place of publick praiſe and thankſgiving, but his heart being rotten, that vitiates all, and (tho it may deceive men) is of no value with God. A ſenſual li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertine being perhaps tyr'd in the purſuit of his pleaſures, or cloy'd
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106444:10"/> with the enjoyment of 'em, may at his leiſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hours look inward a little, and by the light of Nature, (that <hi>witneſs of himſelf,</hi> which God has ſet up in the heart of every man) form ſome honourable thoughts of God; but theſe ſeldom break out into any acts of pure, and ſincere devotion, much leſs into the ſpiritual and exalted ones of Praiſe and Thankſgiving. As for the ſordid worldling, who by fraud, and cruelty, and by grinding the face of the poor, has <hi>made haſt to be rich,</hi> he can have but little reſpect for the true God, having another God of his own: for the Scripture ſays he's an Idolater; he calls Juſtice, and Charity, but ill management, and the Service of God, loſs of time; ſo that there is no ſort of habitual impenitent ſinner that can be any ways fitted for this duty. None but thoſe that <hi>Fear the Lord,</hi> none but thoſe that have fix't in their minds true and genuine notions of his power and goodneſs. Theſe are they whoſe <hi>mouths will ſhew forth his righteouſneſs and ſalvation</hi> all the day long, and will ſay as we all have reaſon to do for his ſignal and repeated mercies, <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord our God who only does wondrous things, and bleſſed be his glorious Name for ever: And let the whole Earth be fill'd with his Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen, Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
